Stanford
University I'll go over it again very
quickly and and then and then tell you
what the higs phenomenon has to do with
masses of cor and
leptons so far I've explained to you
how the gauge
bosons not the photon but the Z and the
W
boson how they
obtain masses from this shift of the
field away from the most symmetric
position which field the higs field but
let's I went through
it in a very simple context where I made
it look very much like ordinary
electrodynamics and I'll continue to do
that but keep in mind we're not talking
about the photon we're talking about
other gauge particles so let's just go
back
to electrodynamics which we're not
really talking about but still the
mathematics is the same there are these
gauge bosons the analoges of
photons the mathematics of them may be a
little more complicated the Symmetry
group may not be U1 it may be su2 or su3
but that's not terribly
important and there is a a dynamics that
leads to Maxwell's equations it's
governed in fact that the simplest way
to encapsulate it is in terms of a lran
you
begin
with a good
pen you begin with the field tensor let
me just remind you what it is it's in
terms
of the vector potential you begin with
that you square it
let's just call it f squared you make
the appropriate uh lenen variant
combination of squares of components of
electric and magnetic field and that's
the
lran and notice it only contains
derivatives of
a and therefore the photon is
massless to have a mass you have to have
you have to get an energy a mass
corresponds to an energy corresponding
to shifting a field homogeneously
everywhere with no
derivatives this has no energy or no no
energy associated with a uniform shift
of the vector potential because only the
derivatives come in and so the photon by
virtue of this is massless it moves with
the speed of light and this simply leads
to Maxwell's equations now you add
something else you add this higs
field the higs field is a field which
corresponds to
charged
particles again I emphasize we're not
talking about ordinary electric charge
we're talking about the charges that
couple to the Z and W bosons the weak
charges and we write this fi in the form
row e to the I Alpha it's a complex
valued field row * e to the I
Alpha and we write down its L grangian
we write its l grangian in terms of
these things that I called covariant
derivatives d f is equal to the
derivative of f plus or I can't remember
if it's plus or minus I uh times the
vector potential time F we write the uh
the lran in terms of those things and
all of a sudden we have an interesting
interaction
between the electromagnetic field and
the charged field here's the here's the
source of the interaction right over
here
that would be basically that would be
electrodynamics ordinary electrodynamics
but now something new happens there's
something new that happens is the
energetics the potential energy of fi
favor something unusual namely that
fi is the minimum value of fi sorry the
minimum value of the potential energy is
not at f equals 0 but at the bottom of
this Mexican hat potential somewh where
is an arbitrary position along there and
so we write that F let's say the radius
of this circle here is f the magnitude
of the field the magnitude of this let's
call it by its name the magnitude of
this higs field is now f is shifted away
from the origin by amount
F and it is also true that the that the
curvature at the bottom here is very
steep so it cost a lot of energy to
shift the field away from the bottom
here and some first approximation we can
just
say that f is simply equal to F the
numerical
number times e to the I Alpha of X only
Alpha is allowed to vary and F is sort
of Frozen Frozen because it takes too
much energy to shift it away from the
minimum but Alpha the angular variable
is still
there all right we could write let me
tell you what happens now we could
take
uh this form for fi and figure out what
the covariant derivative of f is given
that F has this Frozen form where only
Alpha varies I'll write it for you it's
just
equal to the derivative of alpha
plus I
a now all of that gets
multiplied by f * e to the I
Alpha that's the covariant derivative of
y the derivative of
alpha uh sorry I think it's I uh no no
uh no I here plus this and maybe there's
an overall yes I think there's an
overall
I that's what you get when you calculate
the covariant derivative now next thing
we're going to do is multiply this by
its complex conjugate to compute the
action or the lran for for what for f no
f is just a number we've already assumed
that F can't vary very much the lran for
Alpha let's see what we
get we're going to get f s the number f
s that's a
number and then we're going to get
derivative of alpha it's derivative of
alpha with respect to space or time plus
the vector
potential
squared and e to the I Alpha is going to
cancel because we're multiplying it by
its complex
conjugate this is what you get for the
lran of the higs field if you make the
approximation that it's stuck where is
it that it's um stuck and can't move
away from the
minimum I may have I may have blown the
sign but uh did I uh blow the sign I
don't think so but I other term uh no
there was also an I in this term because
when you differentiate fi you'll get I
times the derivative of
alpha all right so both of them have an
ey and I stuck it out over here
oh oh oh oh yeah uh let's see
um yeah I * minus I is 1 yeah I * minus
I you scared me for a minute well it's
not I squ it's I * minus
I well the complex
conjugate involves minus I okay so what
do we get we get this expression over
here now do you remember what a gauge
transformation looks like gauge
transformation which is a symmetry which
is supposed to do nothing to the
physics take any function let's call it
Theta which is what I called it last
time but it could be anything it could
be anything a gauge transformation is to
take a and shift it by the derivative of
theta that's a gauge
transformation okay but look at this
this is a plus the derivative of
something this is a gauge
transformation this is a gauge
transformation where what we have used
for the gauge transformation is not an
arbitrary function Theta but this Alpha
field this Alpha field itself now look
what we have let's redefine a plus the
derivative of alpha it's just a j gauge
transformation of a let's redefine it
let's give it a new name let's call it a
prime okay let's call it a prime this is
f^2 time a prime
squared that's all this is what happens
to F
SAR which originally involved
a what happens to F if we replace a by a
prime
it's completely unchanged because f is
gauge
invariant and so we can also think of f
squ or
F there's this thing over here doesn't
make any difference and what do we find
that the net upshot the net upshot of it
all is to just replace the original
variables by Prime
variables and that's just renaming
that's just a new name for something and
to add a term in the lran which is is
proportional to the square of the vector
potential that was a net
effect just add a
term for the lran for the gauge field
which is proportional to a s no
derivatives in it there no derivatives
in this term here it's just a prime
squared that means that if you were to
shift a prime
everywhere simultaneously you would get
some energy from this term
this term is a Mass for the photon it's
not the photon of course it's the Z and
the W Bon so here's an example of how
this shift of the field from zero to
Value F gives a mass to a particle which
you might have said is not allowed to
have a mass how did it happen the vacuum
shifted to some new spontaneously broken
vacuum and the excitations of the
electromagnetic field in that shifted
vacuum have a mass okay so that's the
higs
phenomena and furthermore the alpha
field is gone it's gone it's been
absorbed into this thing we called a
prime so there's no massless particle
anymore the gold stone Bon has
disappeared it has made a Mass for the
gauge BOS
on and that's it now not quite it there
is still this thing that we
froze in an approximation in an
approximation we said Let's ignore the
oscillations of the field back and forth
in this other
direction if we're giving the system
enough energy if we really poke it hard
enough we can start this higs field
oscillating in the radial Direction
let's call it the radial Direction it's
not a radial Direction in space it's
this radial Direction in field space
those oscillations also are
quanta and they're massive Quanto why
they have a lot of energy even at rest
they oscillate back and forth and those
are the higs
bosons those are the Hig bosons so we
started uh with um massless photons
massless gold stone bosons and massive
higs bosons
and we ended up with massive higs bosons
no gold stone boson and a massive Photon
that's the higs phenomenon okay all
right could you say again why the a
prime squared
indicates a massive yeah whenever you
have
a all right what first of all what is a
mass a mass is an energy a from a field
Theory point of view mass of course is
inertia of a particle or whatever but
from a field the well let go back a step
a mass in special relativity is just the
energy of a system at rest if a system
has no momentum if it's at rest in its
own reference frame then it's the energy
in that reference frame is is the mass
so that's the first step energy at rest
is called mass now what does being at
rest mean being at rest means having no
momentum from a field Theory point of
view from the point of view of
fields or from the point of view of
quantum
mechanics a particle at rest or particle
with zero momentum corresponds to the
Quantum of a field of infinite
wavelength infinite wavelength means the
field doesn't vary at all from point to
point and so a mass what it corresponds
to is an energy stored in a field if you
shift the field simultaneously
everywhere with no derivative no spatial
derivative just shift the field
everywhere simultaneously if you get
some energy that energy is called the
mass okay
well uh we started with a lran and also
an expression for energy which only
involves derivatives of a field if it
only involves derivatives of a field it
means that if we shift the field
everywhere simultaneously we won't get
any
energy so in that sense if this was all
that there
was for the photon then we would say the
photon has no
Mass a uniform shift of the uh Vector
potential would not create any energy we
say the photon has no Mass but now once
there's a term in here like this which
doesn't involve derivatives does not
involve the derivatives of a that means
if we shift a simultaneously everywhere
the response the energy stored in this
term is not zero we shifted a from zero
where the energy was zero to something
else so we got some
energy that uh that energy is called the
mass of the photon so it's
energy stored in does everybody know
what I mean by
homogeneous homogeneous means everywhere
is the same all right if you shift the
photon field everywhere is the same and
you get any energy from it that's the
mass of the
photon in fact in particle physics or in
field theory in general you identify the
mass of a particle as an energy stored
in Shifting the field simultaneously
everywhere it's not just in uh particle
physics in all kinds of
contexts uh I think I talked about them
last time but let me just remember
remind you
again uh a sound wave in a crystal a
sound wave in a crystal corresponds to
uh to a motion
of the crystal lattice which you could
think of as the response to a shift of
the position of the
molecules if you shift the position of
the molecules in a variable way in other
words way down here you shift them to
the left a centimeter and then halfway
down there you shift them to the left a
half a centimeter and then over here you
don't shift them at all and then over
here uh a half a centimeter to the right
and so forth you make a long wavelength
um it's called a phonon a long
wavelength phonon but it's a kind of
wave in the crystal where where very
slowly varying and there's energy stored
in that you've deformed the crystal a
little
bit that energy is called the energy of
a phonon now what happens if you shift
the crystal everywhere simultaneously by
exactly the same amount we could call
that a homogeneous shift do we get any
energy from that no so so a homogeneous
shift where everything is shifted
simultaneously all together that gives
no energy and so you would say phons are
massless phonons have no Mass which
means that a phonon with zero
momentum has no
energy phonons
photons
spinons uh spinons are uh are in magnets
they have to do with the orientation of
the little fun mental
magnets if you reorient the magnets in a
variable way from place to place you get
a little bit of energy it's called a
spin wave if you rotate all the magnets
together simultaneously everywhere it
costs no energy you just rotated the
magnet so that's another example of
waves which at infinite wavelength or
homogeneous waves have no energy they're
also
massless I thought we started out this
analysis with a particle that was
vibrating a little bit in
Alpha yeah and now and and that that
originally before we coupled it to a to
the vector potential its energy was
purely row
SAR D well it's just let's call it f
squ d alpha squared that's all it was it
was just a square of this thing where
the vector potential was completely
absent from the problem
okay now because it only involves
derivatives if we shift Alpha everywhere
simultaneously in other words everywhere
is in space we shift the
angle instead of saying the field has
the value over here we put it over here
everywhere is in space that cost no
energy it cost no energy because it
didn't make any
derivatives I'm not sure what the
question was but does that answer it
well by shifting it you're changing
Alpha you're changing Alpha and that
means but it's derivatives of alpha
which give you energy oh CU you're not
continuously moving it in Alpha that's
right you're not moving it you're not
changing it from place to place if you
change it from place to place that's the
energy of the gold stone B on all right
but if you shift it everywhere
simultaneously then it costs no energy
why because the energy only involves
gradients okay so that's the idea so
keep that in mind that's a buzzword uh
that mass stands for energy at
rest uh but it also stands for energy
associated with uniform homogeneous
shifts of fields fields or whatever it
is we're talking
about there is an interesting example to
see to get uh to get an idea of how Mass
can happen I explained to you that if
you have a crystal and you move all the
molecules simultaneously it doesn't cost
any energy now supposing your crystal
lattice was composed of particles which
themselves had both plus some plus
charges and some minus charges okay so
these are
molecules ions plus ions and minus ions
or they it could just be atoms they
could be the protons that the the nuclei
at the center and the electrons around
them and supposing you did the following
you
shifted all of the electrons to the left
uniformly and all the protons to the
right
uniformly that would be called a
homogeneous shift just a little bit just
a little separation between the electron
cloud and the nuclei do you think that
would cost any energy you bet because
you would have pulled the uh the plus
charges away from the minus
charges that would be a homogeneous
shift of not Fields but locations which
would cost energy what do you think
would happen if you made that shift the
the the plus particles this way the
minus particles this way what'll happen
next it'll start to vibrate okay it will
not behave the way it would if
everything was moved simultaneous l so
moving everything simultaneously that's
a zero momentum
phonon moving the plus charges relative
to the minus charges what is that called
anybody
know a plasmon a plasmon plasmons have
mass phonons do not
okay
thees deres include
what oh yeah absolutely absolutely about
shifting
things is doesn't the time component yes
yes yes yes yes what you're saying is
right but I'm just imagining spatially
shifting everything and not inducing any
time
derivatives
well all right we good no no it's a good
question over no no no by by shifting I
don't mean an actual process I just mean
a mathematical change in what you mean
by the vacuum right or you do it
extremely slowly very very slowly move
it from here to here uh yes you're right
these the um the actual energy contains
time derivatives also but I was simply
the same is true incidentally of the
crystal
lce what are the time derivatives of the
shifts the kinetic energy the velocities
of the molecules so if you really give
the uh Crystal a shift which means it's
moving off with a velocity
then of course this kinetic energy so
when I said a shift I meant a shift in
your imagination where you shift
everything simultaneously and started
out at rest compared to where originally
was also at rest good but that's a good
point okay let's talk now about Fons
this means electrons
muons and so
forth uh and where they get their Mass
from it turns turns out the real
electron muon quirks also get their
Mass from this higs phenomenon from this
spontaneous symmetry
breaking and let's discuss what we know
about it the first thing we go back to
is the basics of the the of not the
theory but actual experimental data
about weak interactions this could be
beta Decay the decay of a neutron to a
proton but uh uh and an electron and
anti-
neutrino okay here's what goes back
to
uh 50s the 50s no earlier than the 50s I
think I think I don't remember exactly
when uh the following fact was
discovered first of all uh
reflection
symmetry which means reflection of space
left hand into right hand is not a good
symmetry of
nature it's an ancient fact from the 50s
that it was discovered that the
reflection the mirror reflection of a
process is not another possible process
now in Quantum
electrodynamics the mirror image of any
process is another possible process that
itself is a symmetry it's not a
continuous symmetry it's a discrete
symmetry you take everything and you
reflect it you don't rotate it you
reflect it you take the left hand and
the right there's no hand which is um
sort of Midway uh there's no continuous
way to go from Left Hand to right hand
so replacing every Left Hand by a right
hand or every left left uh screw thread
with a right screw thread and so forth
that's a symmetry of quantum
electrodynamics and it's also a symmetry
of quantum Chrome
Dynamics it is not a symmetry of the
weak interactions left and right are
fundamentally different and it's
different as they can be so let me tell
you what the experimental fact
is
that the decay of a
neutron Neutron which gives a
proton an
electron and an anti- neutrino
well let's first talk about the
handedness of particles is there any
sense in which particles are handed have
a handedness like my hands yes there is
they have a spin they also have a
direction of
motion right if the spin is along the
direction of motion in other words there
are two possibilities the spin can be
oriented along the direction of motion
or it can be oriented OPP opposite to
the direction of motion in quantum
mechanics of course if the spin is
oriented in some other direction you can
build it up out of superpositions of the
two states along the direction of motion
and opposite all right so an electron
moving along with a high momentum for
example can either have it spin along
the direction of motion that means it's
rotating with a right hand screw thread
okay it's rotating or
spinning uh with a right- hand sco that
that's called a right-handed electron
and an electron can also be a
left-handed electron that simply means
its spin is going uh is helically going
in the opposite direction so there are
two kinds of electrons right-handed and
left-handed now um what happens in a
beta Decay like this you might think you
could either make right-handed or
left-handed
electrons right-handed and left-handed
electrons are as good as each other in
every respect in Quantum electrodynamics
there are no processes which are not
symmetric if you can make a right-handed
electron in some process then there's a
reflected process which is also a
possible process where you can make a
left-handed electron if right is
possible left is
possible
nevertheless when the process of beta
Decay became something where you could
really do with precision and study the
handedness of the electron that come out
they're always
left-handed there is never a process it
doesn't matter what orientation the spin
of the neutron has no matter what you do
the electrons which come out are always
left-handed uh this goes beyond the
theory of beta Decay any weak
interaction process in other words any
process where
a w boson for example where a w
boson interacts and takes a electron
into a
neutrino or where you interchange uh you
know where you flip these lines to make
uh to make different processes out of it
it's always the left-handed electron
which interacts with the w BOS on never
a right-handed
electron so for example you could
imagine a process where uh an electron
scatters off something changes into a
nutrino and there's something over here
that it scatters off a proton or
something else or another electron
You'll Always Find that the left-handed
electron scatters and the right-handed
electron doesn't this is uh this is a
fact and the same thing is true of the
nutrino incidentally it's always a
left-handed
nutrino it's questionable whether a
right handed nutrino exists incidentally
this is a question which we've not
answered uh we'll come back to it
another time but there certainly exist
both right-handed and left-handed
electrons we think there are also
probably right-handed and left-handed
neutrinos all right so electrons so
there's something asymmetric Left Right
asymmetric about
um about the weak
interactions and it is what is it it is
that the left-handed electrons are
charged with respect to the W boson in
other words we could imagine a situation
in electrodynamics which would be
similar it's an untrue situation don't
let me say right now this is not correct
right but we could imagine a world in
which only left-handed
electrons are
charged left-handed electrons could
scatter off photons or could produce
protons and become left-handed electrons
and which right-handed electrons could
not we could imagine it it's not true we
say it over and over it is not true but
imagine it then you would say that the
left-handed electron has an electric
charge and the right hand an electron
does not now that's bizarre I mean
that's that's really bizarre okay and
it's not true but with respect to the
weak interactions not the emission of a
photon but the emission of a w Boson
it is as if the left-handed particles
carried charge associated with the
emission of a gauge boson and the
right-handed particles did
not that's a very strange fact it's uh
an empirical
fact what's that it's also true of
quirks it is also true of
quirks
um with so we have to we're going to
modify the statement a little bit but at
some deep level it's exactly
true okay let's talk about left-handed
and right-handed particles uh Fons and
let's go back to the dra
equation and I will tell you a little
bit about the connection between the dur
equation and the handedness of particles
I'm not going to spend a lot of time I'm
just going to give you the rough
outlines of the idea
let's go back to the dur equation the
dur equation looked something like
this
i d s by DT this is the direct field
which could correspond to the electron
it could correspond to the muon it could
be the field for quirks they all have
the same form the D
equations the uh time derivative of the
direct field and remember what the
direct field is is it's a four component
object
where the four
components correspond to let's say two
different
subdivisions the particles can have spin
along either axis that gives you two
components up Spin and down Spin and the
particles can have positive or negative
energy remember direct particles can
have positive or negative energy now
we've learned over and over again that
the negative energy particles should be
replaced by antiparticles with positive
energy but in the
mathematics uh the direct field has four
components UPS spin positive energy down
spin positive energy upspin negative
energy down spin positive energy or you
can think of it as UPS Spin and down
spin of particle an
antiparticle okay so there are four
components to the direct field and the
components think of it as a four
component column
Vector there are
matrices 4x4 matrices called the da
matrices D call them
Alpha three Alphas sorry three Alphas
one for each direction of
space let's call them Alpha I for the
three directions of space times the
derivative of the field with respect to
X sub
I this would be the direct
equation if the particle had no mass now
how can you see that you can see that
because the equation only involves
derivatives of the
field if the
field the whole dynamics of the field
only involves derivatives of the field
we've seen in previous situations that
when the Dynamics of the field only
involves derivatives the field is
massless there's no restoring Force no
tendency for the field to
oscillate unless it has a
gradient no time derivative unless
there's a space derivative so if you
shift the field sigh everywhere
simultaneously it does not create an
oscillation does not create any
energy right what do you put on the
right hand side if you want to have a
Mass for the field well there was a
fourth direct Matrix called
beta you put the mass time beta Time
s that's the dir
equation
now the electron could be moving along
with a momentum a momentum means is a
gradient of the field s it means a plain
wave but that's not so important and the
spin can either be along the direction
of motion or opposite to the direction
of motion those two components we can
think of that as the left-handed
components of the direct field and the
right-handed components so let me write
these equations for you this is four
equations one for each component let's
write them for the left and right-handed
components
separately here's what it looks like
I times the derivative of the
right-handed
component of the direct field describing
electrons plus I Alpha I derivative of
the right-handed
field is
equal now you might think that the right
thing to put here is something involving
the right-handed field but it turns out
this ba this Matrix beta interchanges
right hand and left hand
so a mass term over here
corresponds to a coupling between
right-handed and
left-handed and likewise here's the
equation for the left-handed
component DCI left-handed by
DT turns out it's minus I Alpha sub i d
left-handed by
dxi is equal to m s
right-handed in other words it's a funny
equation in which the right-handed and
the left-handed components are
completely
independent if the mass is zero but the
mass mixes them
up roughly speaking you can think of a
direct electron as one which as it moves
along oscillates between left and
right and
the oscillation is the mass
term but let's let's not push that too
hard it's not quite right um the mass
term couples together the left-handed
and right-handed
components this is for a direct particle
what a mass term is it's a thing which
couples together it's a it's a m it's an
energy which is only there if both the
left-handed and the right-handed
components are both
excited okay now we can see what are
some odd
things let's suppose that only the
left-handed direct particle had a
charge which is true with respect to the
weakened directions not true with
respect to the electromagnetic but let's
just pretend only the left-handed
electron has a charge the right-handed
electron has no
charge okay
a fictitious
world is this equation allowable
then well it's not because the meaning
of this
equation is that a right-handed particle
moving along will turn into a
left-handed
particle I'll explain it another way in
a second and a left-handed particle
moving along will turn into a
right-handed
particle what does this mean it means
that charge conservation would be
violated a left a right-handed field
becoming a left-handed field would
violate charge
conservation another way to say it is to
remember that a Charged field if a field
has charge it gets multiplied under a
gauge transformation or under one of
these U1 Transformations it gets
multiplied by e to the I Theta if it has
no charge it does not get multiplied by
e to the I Theta now we look at this
equation this
equation if the right-handed field is
neutral has no charge then under a U1
transformation nothing would happen to
the left-and side but the right hand
side would pick up a factor of e to the
I Theta likewise over here the left hand
I Theta the right hand side would not
these are equations cannot be symmetric
if only s
left is multiplied by e to the I Theta
and not s right that's another way of
saying that charge conservation would
not permit a mixing of left and right
like this
if um if only the left-handed electron
were charged
both of them are charged in reality and
because both of them carry the same
charge you can go back and forth from
left to right without violating charge
conservation
yeah
Wonder on
are probably
not no they're probably not oh no no no
no I meant that
sorry no you're right they're not
consistent yeah I pull the whole eye out
on the outside you're right okay yeah
okay so it's just basic charge
conservation would
forbid the possibility of a Mass for the
electron if only left-handed electrons
had charge or if only right-handed
electrons had
charge fortunately for the real world
that's not true electrons both
right-handed and electron and
left-handed have charge the electron has
a mass the world would be very different
if the electron didn't have a mass and
uh
um chemistry wouldn't exist yeah and we
wouldn't be in a happy
world how would the world be different
if if right-handed electrons could be
emitted from weak interaction as well as
up hand it's both right-handed and
left-handed we'll come to it we'll come
to it
it would be very different
but
um but we will come to
it okay
so let's come to the weekend Yeah
question you can you can measure the
spin of electron vertically unless they
select the ones that are pointing upward
and if you accelerate those in that
direction do you say they have a spin as
the type that you're talking here the
same thing M okay thank there's an
interesting question is it
possible that there would only be one
kind of electron namely only left-handed
electrons okay yes it is but only if a
massless so let me explain why supposing
there was only a left-handed electron
that means it spins only to the left
when it moves you know it has a a
left-handed helical kind of motion all
right now if the electron has a
mass you could imagine slowing it down
and bringing it to rest bringing it to
rest in a way that doesn't change its
angular momentum you can bring a you
could exert a force on it which doesn't
uh change its angular momentum so in
that case you would take this electron
which is moving along rotating to the
left with a left-handed motion bring it
to rest and even go past that bring it
back the other way it's rotation s of
rotation hasn't changed that's just
angular momentum conservation but its
direction of velocity has changed it has
turned into a right-handed uh
electron if I I I judge by my thumb if
it's moving in that direction then the
direction of my fingers is its
handedness so if it's rotating that way
and moving that way it's left-handed but
if it's rotating that way and moving
that way it's right-handed
so if the particle has a mass you can
always bring it to rest and over
decelerate it and send it off in the
opposite
direction and you guaranteed then that
you've taken a left-handed electron and
turned it into
right-handed okay if it has a mass what
if it has no
mass then you simply can't bring it to
rest you simply cannot do this process
of taking it moving in that direction
slowing it down bring it to rest what
you can do is rotate it around but that
does not change I don't change my left
hand to my right hand when I rotate
around but uh if I can bring it to rest
then you can be sure that both kinds
have if I can bring it to rest I can be
sure that both kinds necessarily have to
exist you can only bring an object to
rest if it has a mass so there's another
way of thinking about uh yeah
a circularly polarized
Photon okay it changes its
polarization if it's rotating that way
and it bounces off the mirror it will
continue to rote that way but it will go
in the opposite direction that means
it's changed from circular polarization
right-handed to Circular polarization
left-handed so the photon is also but
never to rest well that's right it never
came to rest right right okay if the if
you had a particle which only could have
one helicity helicity means this
handedness then you couldn't have a
mirror that reflected it a
point
yeah I generally have both but because
okay because real electrons have a mass
it means the electron the real electron
is a mix both kinds of
hand
Focus why would it be difficult to
focus well that doesn't make it hard to
focusing focusing doesn't have to do
with their spin it has to do with their
position I'm not sure what the point
is say it again
the left-handed and the right-handed it
could happen depending it depends on
what exactly what's focusing it
now to a good
approximation left-handed and
right-handed particles in an electric or
magnetic field behave the same way they
have the same trajectories not quite
because of the difference of the
Magnetic Moment right so magnetic
moments are small
of an
electron and and if you have a gradient
of an electric field or a gradient of a
magnetic field
well a magnetic field in general I think
what you're saying is a magnetic field
will affect the left-handed and the
right-handed electrons differently yeah
this is true yeah that's
right that can happen
right okay so how so here we are we're
in a world
of does this the fact that left-handed
and right-handed are different is that
just an accident of nature or is that is
it what is that just an accident of
nature or probably not an accident of
nature it's it's it's it's not an
accident of nature but for the moment
let's treat it as an accident of nature
an empirical fact that we know for the
moment
okay all right if it's true that the
mathematical dur
equation if the left-handed particle and
the right-handed particle have different
charge then the direct equation or the
symmetry of the uh system will not allow
us to mix right-handed and left-handed
like that then the question is how much
the electron get a charge I get a mass
excuse me how might it get a mass in
this fake
World in which left-handed and
right-handed electrons have different
electric charge I use electric charge
just because it's familiar and I want to
make this
uh but it's really the weak interaction
forces that we're interested in all
right let's imagine that there's another
field let's make it a ban field a ban
field
Y and this boson field
f is also
charged let's say it has plus charge
boson field means its quanta have
positive
charge let's write down the rules of
transformation under these U1 symmetries
first of all all right let's write them
over here under a U1 transformation s
left goes to e to the I Theta s left why
because left-handed electrons are
charged what happens to S right somebody
yell
out it just goes to S right it doesn't
transform at
all and what happens to
fi it's charged right it's charged by
assumption depending on the sign of the
charge let's say it goes the same way as
this one e to the I Theta
F okay now let's come back to the dra
equation over here clearly the equation
as it stands is not invariant under this
operation the left hand side of the top
equation does not transform the right
hand side does transform same thing with
the lower equation except opposite but
now let's play a trick
let's take this Mass throw the mass out
for the
moment and put in here an orbit a
constant some
unknown constant which we'll fix later a
numerical constant
times F let's see left-handed one
transforms times F
star and this one times
f is this legal
now this one doesn't transform at all
right what about
this s left gets a phase but five gets
or F star gets the opposite
phase so we haven't violated the
Symmetry the U1 symmetry how about this
one
no what know it's good or no it's bad no
it is good let's see s right does not
transform at all and I think s left and
fi transform the same way right so F
right doesn't transform at all s left
picks up the factor of e to the I Theta
but so does
f so both of these equations are now
consistent with the
Symmetry this is a perfectly good
um alteration of the dra equation which
does not violate charge conservation
there's another way to think about it
you can think about this picture as
saying a right-handed the leftand side
represents the propagation of a
right-handed particle and the right hand
side represents the splitting into a
left-handed
particle and I guess it's a fi particle
fire oppos AN anti-i particle so a
neutral particle breaks up into a
left-handed particle which has charge
and a right-handed particle which has
the opposite
charge that's what this equation means
particle propagating along makes a
transition to two particles one is
Left-Handed and one is of a fi star type
conserves charge and the you can say the
same about this one over here a
left-handed particle moves along and
becomes a fi and a right-handed
particle that also conserves charge so
that's the way you can think about this
it just describes a new kind of process
in which lefts and rights
can turn into each other but only at the
cost of emitting charged particles to
compensate the charge what's the
probability for emitting such a particle
what's the strength of this interaction
it's this constant G
the G is called a coupling constant it's
not the electromagnetic charge it's none
of the it's none of the coupling
constants we've we've already described
it's called a ukawa
coupling all right now let's come back
to fi let's suppose fi is one of these
magical higs
Fields supposing fi is one of these
magical higs Fields remember the higs
field or is also a charge carrying field
and let's suppose it has the form row e
to the I
Alpha in
addition something which is definitely
not true of Electro Dynamics let's
suppose this F field has a spontaneous
gives rise to a spontaneous symmetry
breaking so that in fact it has
magnitude
F let's forget Alpha for the moment
remember Alpha what happened to Alpha it
got eaten by the higs phenomena and
disappeared out of the system but row
itself or F was just proportional to
this F quantity or was f f was just the
shift of the field away from the origin
then what happens over
here right fi is too rigid to get
excited very easily and so it's just
approximated by a constant this just
becomes
approximately G
f s left this becomes approximately
g
f so
WR seate
g g is just a number so is f they can't
be
separated well okay here's how we
separate them we go back remember what
happened to the photon in this fake
World it got a mass equal to f so we
look at the photon and we say the
photon not the real Photon I really mean
the Z and the w we look at the Z and the
W and that tells us what f is then we
look
at the Fons and we see what G is all
right but what is this combination this
combination is playing exactly the same
role as the original mass in the dra
equation so another magical example of
how a shift in the higs field gives rise
to masses for particles the masses for
particles simply mean meaning the
coupling between left and
right-handed left goes to right-handed
we identify that is the mass of a feron
and here we see that it can happen but
only if the Symmetry is spontaneously
broken okay so the higs phenomena has
another role it gives the Fons
Mass how big is the mass of the
Fons the mass of a
firon is equal to some
G time
F now there are different firion in our
world there's the electron there's the
muon there are the various quarks that
only means that there are a collection
of different G's in the
world these G's are called yukawa
couplings and there's one for each kind
of firon is an electron yukawa
coupling let's estimate how big is the
electron yukawa coupling remember that
the mass of the Z boson or the W boson
is essentially F anybody know what the
mass of a w boson
is that's about 900 gev right did
somebody say how
much sorry 90 gev not 900 thank you 90 G
roughly 100 gev
what's the mass of an electron so we
could be talking about electrons here
this would be the ukawa coupling for the
electron half an me right
so G electron here must be a very small
number what is it it's uh it's the ratio
of the electron Mass to the Z mass and
that's 100 gev versus half an me that's
a th big number hundreds of thousands
how many how
much 200
what that's 100 gev versus a half an
me okay the difference between an me and
a gev is a factor of a thousand so it's
roughly a factor of 10 to this number is
about 10 to the
minus5 very very small number how do we
know it we know it from knowing both the
mass of the boson and the mass of the
electron
next what's the next one the next one is
the muon or the upcar or the down quark
and there's a variety of different
numbers what's the heaviest of the uh
quarks the top quark and what is that
how much what's its
mass it's uh about a factor of one and a
half or two times somewhere between one
and a half and two times uh uh times the
mass of the W so that means for the the
top
quk this number
here is a number of order
one so there's a whole spectrum of these
different ukawa couplings that nobody
understands but one thing that's
interesting is you and you say so okay
so all you've done is
fit a uh a collection of numbers to the
masses of the firion but now you can
hope for an experimental conserv uh
experimental confirmation of these
numbers let's go
back to the coupling of the right-handed
and the left-handed particles here and
remember that F was simply the Frozen
value of the higs
field but the higs field is not really
Frozen it really can shift
around what is the Hig field the Hig
field is the fluctuation away from this
Frozen value the real higs particle the
real higs particle is the fluctuation
away from here so in fact what we should
really write if we're doing it correctly
is write
f plus the higs
field times s
left what is this telling us this is
telling us that sorry this right this is
right I think no left yeah left this is
telling us that a process can happen
where a right-handed
firon can turn into a left-handed firmon
and a higs particle a real
process left right-handed particle can
become a left-handed particle and a higs
particle and what's the amplitude for
that the same yukawa
coupling
that yukawa yukawa was a Japanese
physicist sorry
yukawa
Yuka Yuka was a Japanese physicist in
the
40s who
uh among other things wrote down the
mathematics of the couplings between
fermans and bans like this
right uh won the Nobel Prize for for
this in 194 40s for different physics
for nuclear physics uh applications of
these ideas but in any case the point is
that the same coupling constant which
appears in the mass of the
Fons also governs the process of a feron
becoming a higs boson and another Fon I
should draw these as solid
lines feron left-handed becomes Fon
right-handed and a higs boson
now we've not detected the Hig bosons
yet we've not detected them yet so it
becomes a very very important thing once
the Hig boson is detected to study the
different processes in which higs bosons
are produced to see that the relative
probabilities of producing a higs boson
by an electron and by a top quk or
another kind of Quirk that they have the
same ratios as these constants here for
example it tells us that in the decay of
the higs boson this could be read as the
decay of a higs boson into a pair of
Fons that it prefers to Decay into the
heaviest
Fons if it has enough energy to do so it
will preferentially Decay to heavier
Fons rather than light
fion and uh that's a consequence of this
because the couplings here are
larger so that's one of the things that
will become important in uh in the LHC
is to study the properties of higs
bosons and see if we can detect evidence
for these coupling constants Yeah so
basically all the coupling constants
regardless of where they come in are
really probability numbers the square
roots of
probability
MH sometimes they're fourth roots of
probabilities you know it depends on how
many times you have to square but uh
yeah right they're related to
probabilities and and
um so there's an assumption here that
there's only one such higs post on that
everything I have made the assumption
that there's only one type of higs bons
in various more complicated theories
beyond the standard model there are
often more than one and then much of
what I have to say for example there are
higs BOS on well yeah there super
symmetric models they're usually two
higs bosons but uh then you just modify
it accordingly and and of course much of
what I say have to has to be
modified uh because the weak
interactions are su2 not U1 so what I'm
doing is giving you a kind of simplified
version of what the higs phenomena
does but thus far taking into account
all of the various gauge
interactions here's an interesting
fact all of the particles that are seen
in the standard model could not have a
mass if it were not for this shift s for
the shift of the higs
field the gagee bosons they normally do
not have
mass and the only way to give them the
mass the only known way to give them
mass is this phenomenon of spontaneous
symmetry breaking associated with the
eggs field their mass is typically
proportional just to this F right so the
Z and W B on all of the Fons because of
the peculiar property that the weak
interactions are purely
left-handed the symmetries of the gauge
theories do not allow you to just write
down a you know in other words to
postulate a mathematical Mass term for
these fans the only way that they get
mass is through this shift of the field
to say it yet another way all of the
masses of the known particles are such
that they are
proportional to this simp symmetry
breaking parameter F the shift of the
higs
field that's a curiosity which may be
deep it may be important Yeah question
if you have antiparticles and they Decay
beta Decay would would the the direction
be the opposite yes okay yeah that's a
good point uh if a if an electron is
purely left-handed then its antiparticle
is purely
right-handed but nevertheless we
continue to call it left-handed I mean
we call it uh we still say the electron
is Left-Handed
yeah leftand an
elron the positron would be right-handed
the positron which interacts with the Z
and W
right so youy hand you qualify by it
handness not by the handedness of
it uh it's just a pure convention we we
have a lot more more experience with
electrons than we do with positrons so
we tend to name things by the we tend to
say the electron meaning the full
complex of objects that go together with
the electron are called left-handed
nevertheless the positron
right we
do well an electron and a positron if
collided together can make for example a
zebon so I guess I guess it would be a
left-handed electron and a right-handed
positron uh could make a zbo
on no no no you can create positrons in
all kinds of
ways uh you hit any particle hard enough
with anything and it will make among
other things
positrons right certainly not all
positrons in nature are made of
a for example you can make positrons by
just colliding an electron with a
photon you hit an electron hard enough
with a photon and you'll make the
electron won't disappear but out will
come an extra electron and and a
positron okay for example let's see if
we can work out the findan diagram that
describes
that okay so the findan diagrams basic
findan diagram
or the basic vertex is electron electron
and
Photon but if we flip the lines around
we can turn this into electron let's
call this e
minus e+ that's positron and Photon or
better yet let's see so what did I say
we said electron collides with a photon
and makes an extra electron and positron
okay so here's the photon colliding with
the
electron then another Photon emitted and
that Photon turning into an electron and
a
positron right so that's a findan
diagram a fairly complicated findan
diagram uh that would take an electron
and a photon and turn it into an
electron two electrons and a positron so
there's all kinds of processes that can
make positrons
the accelerator can you select the speed
of
the well you're asking in practice how
much can you U not that much so yes you
can you can uh you can change the energy
of the
uh varying the magnetic fields and so
forth I I had thought that one of the
last experiments I did slack is with
polarized electrons polarized electrons
yeah it's hard to make polarized
electrons but once you make them you can
accelerate them so the electrons are
made
in slow electrons are made which are
polarized don't ask me how they're
polarized I don't remember but uh then
they're accelerated as polarized
electron if you remember it's a very low
energy spin orbit interaction that
selects a
particular yeah but the details of how I
I can't remember it's it's not easy to
do you need big magnetic fields and it
took a while to for them to uh to to
generate the technology to do U
polarized electron
beams polarized means all the spins are
in the same direction
yeah yeah so what about
neutrinos okay so neutrinos all right so
in the standard model and in Old Time
physics of the uh before recent years it
was not known whether the nutrin it was
thought that the nutrino was massless
now the mass of the nutrino is very very
small remember there are several
different neutrinos electron neutrinos
muon neutrinos very small uh within
experimental error they move with a
speed of
light and that means that it's possible
for them to have only a
single-handed right in the standard
model neutrinos all are left-handed the
the standard model does not even contain
anything that you could call
right-handed neutrinos
uh generalizations of the standard model
have right-handed neutrinos but those
right-handed neutrinos typically have a
very large mass and uh it's a
complicated story maybe we'll come to it
but in the simple standard model
um uh neutrinos are massless now do we
know are they really massless they're
not we know they're not we know they're
not because of nutrino oscillations so
we know they're not but their masses are
very small 10us 3 electron volts are
even smaller and uh
so
uh in
um approximately they're very close to
massless they're not
quite what actually happens to neutrino
is really curious remember a mass term
is a thing which turns left-handed to
right-handed right so it's a process in
which left-handed can make a transition
to
right-handed now uh what happens with
the
nutrino there are left-handed neutrinos
and of course they go along with
right-handed anti- neutrinos if the
nutrino is Left-Handed then the anti-
nutrino is
right-handed and one way of having a
mass for the neutrino is to have a
left-handed nutrino make transitions to
right-handed anti- neutrinos mass is
always for Fons it's always left hand
turns into right hand turns into left
hand turns into the right hand processes
which involve that for neutrinos
curiously the right-handed particle
which the nutrino can make a transition
to uh is the antiparticle of the left uh
left-handed nutrino so that's an
interesting um fact why could why could
the electron the real electron why could
the real electron not get a mass by
mixing by the left-handed electron with
the right-handed positron
it'd be pretty yeah you'd be pretty
amazed to see a electron turned into a
positron because it violates charge
conservation so that's not an option for
the electron why is it allowed for the
nutrino has no charge has no charge
right uh the buzzword terminology for a
particle which gets a
mass from a DA equation it's very
curious um the thing on the right hand
side here is the anti-particle of the
thing on the left hand side for nutrino
a particle which gets its mass by mixing
in this way with its anti-particle is
called a mayorana
particle
mayorana was Mayana
the
uh young Italian
physicist I'm not even sure what year uh
mayorana ET mayorana who disappeared
shortly after uh inventing the mayorana
particle and never was heard of again I
don't mean he wasn't academically heard
of I mean he was never heard of again
nobody knows what happened to
him Mafia doesn't are you going be able
tell us why we think the is going to be
reached the mass of it will be yeah we
can we can talk about turns out the mass
of the higs particle is also generated
by the higs particle and is also ordered
the same F so we more or less expect
that the higs particle will have the
same order of magnitude mass as the W
and zbo on somewhat heavier but uh but
more or less the same but okay so let's
think about now what we found this is
somewhat striking all
masses in the standard model Trace back
to this parameter f if F were zero they
would all be
massless right all the particles of the
standard model with a possible exception
of the higs BOS on itself but all the
particles of the standard model all the
familiar guys there and even many of the
unfamiliar ones Z and W and so forth top
quirks bottom quirks the whole
works uh all of their
masses are a response to this F they're
all propor to F in the formulas of
particle physics why is that why are
there no particles in nature whose
masses um might not be much much larger
than
F Well maybe there are particles which
masses are much larger than F we just
haven't discovered them yet why not
because the are the limits of our
energies are roughly at about that level
now this number F in order to agree with
with the masses of Z and W bosons this
number F thought of as a mass is about
gev if there were particles in nature
whose Mass were much larger than 200 gev
or so we would not have discovered
them right supposing there were
particles let me give you an example of
a particle in this context in this uh
slightly fictitious but uh but still
qualitatively correct
context where a particle could get a
mass that was not due to the higs boson
suppose we had a particle in this weak
interaction context where both the
left-handed and the right-handed
components both had the same
charge with respect to these weak
interactions suppose such a particle
existed then there would be no
obstruction to having a mass
which had nothing whatever to do with
f it could have a mass which would be
arbitrarily
big it could be much much bigger than f
it could be 10 to the 16th times bigger
than or even bigger than F there would
be no obstruction to it having a mass
having nothing to do with this
F uh there are other kinds of particles
that could have masses which are not due
to this F the thinking now is that the
natural Mass scale of elementary
particle physics wherever it comes from
we can talk about where it comes from is
much much bigger than
F any particle that can have a
mass will have a mass and that mass will
be much much bigger than f it is only
those particles for which there are
symmetries which are the are deep
underlying reason s why in the absence
of spontaneous symmetry breaking they
can't have mass the gauge bons
themselves the photon is one of them uh
these particles which are purely
left-handed they are forbidden from
having Mass unless there's a spontaneous
symmetry breaking so maybe it's not so
surprising that all the particles which
have low enough energy to have been
detected all are the ones whose masses
are coming from the same origin namely a
small amount of spontaneous symmetry
Breaking All the Other particles which
could have masses independent of this F
simply apparently have masses at some
scale which is much larger that's the
thinking uh so it's not in that sense
the particle Spectrum as we know it
consists of the particles which would
have been massless
if the Symmetry was not spontaneously
broken they're all responses to a small
amount of spontaneous symmetry
breaking
uh that's the thinking in any case this
may or may not be true does that mean
that they
don't play a large role in
reality well
um definitely could mean that it depends
of course on what you mean by reality
which which ones don't play a big role
on with the finite masses oh the ones
which can have masses
uh they do not play much role in
ordinary physics now one exception is
the possibility of dark
matter the best guesses about theories
of dark matter is that the masses of
them are much significantly larger than
this F possibly by a factor of 10 larger
than this F for such particles it's
unreasonable for various reasons to
think that they get their mass in this
way and so dark matter particles may be
the first indication of a spectrum of
particles whose masses do not come from
spontaneous symmetry breaking that's
thinking in general at least this
particular spontaneous symmetry breaking
uh yeah what is the mass of
cosmic well depends cosmic rays can be
electrons they can be protons they can
be photons what their mass is is the
mass of those
particles they're very high energy but
Mass means energy at rest right what is
all right so you could ask me what is
the energy of cosmic rays well basically
anything up to about 10 to the 21
electron volts
so 10 21 what's 21 - 9 12 uh 21 - 9 is
12 10 12
G which is very very high higher than
any accelerator that we're going to
build uh incidentally cosmic ray
collisions in a certain sense will not
be as high in energy probe as
accelerator probes and the reason is
because the cosmic ray is banging into a
particle at rest
the hron collider will collide together
two particles and it's you may think of
it as twice the energy but it's much
more potent than that we can come to
why
uh uh hitting a particle at rest with a
high
energy is not typically as potent as
hitting two particles uh headon with a
good deal lower energy so what will be
measured
in CERN
will be processes
energies uh 10 um no still not as high
still not as high as the highest cosmic
rays
um one term that you don't use or you
use in frequently here is inertia is
inertia and mass essentially the same
thing yeah well yes yes and now you can
ask by what magic is it that
inertia and these expressions in the
equations and so forth correspond to the
same physical idea and that's more
complicated um but you could go back to
Bas basic
relativity and you could have asked
special relativity you could have asked
the same question there definition two
different definitions of of mass one of
them is inertia all right how hard it is
to get a thing accelerating and the
other is energy at
rest why is the energy of an object at
rest related to the inertia of how much
how hard it is to accelerate
it that is contained in the rules of
special relativity but once you know
that then you might as well focus on the
definition of mass as energy at
rest right so the question does not have
to do with particle physics it doesn't
have to do it has to do with special
relativity so so once obtains mass does
it start to CPL the gravity field
exactly well it couples yeah yes this is
that's right
um good
so that's correct once it gets Mass it
starts to couple to the gravity field
now that's a little bit um not quite
accurate photons don't have
Mass photons do couple to the gravity
field what is it about photons that what
is it that really couples to the gravity
field it's energy energy energy is the
thing which really couples to the
gravitational field how do we know that
photons coupled to the gravitational
field they bend the trajectories of a
photon are deflected in a gravitational
field action equals reaction and so that
means that the orbit of the Sun is
slightly perturbed every time a photon
goes past it but that's pretty
negligible but just the fact that uh
that photons are deflected when they go
around the Sun means that that massless
particles do couple to gravity but
um uh particles at rest their energy is
simply their Mass so if you have two
particles more or less at rest the
gravitational interaction between them
is related to their
Mass resistance to acceleration is also
related resistance to acceleration is
also related to total mass it's related
to to energy to not just to energy not
just indeed it is indeed it is that's
correct uh the resistance to
acceleration of a high energy particle
is um bigger than the particle at rest
yeah the only the only subtlety is that
the resist let's call it the resistance
the resistance to acceleration if a
particle is moving down the z-axis
then there's a different effective
inertia of it if you make a force along
the z-axis or if you make a force
perpendicular to the z-axis so there's
no Universal concept of mass unique mass
for a particle which is moving depends
on which way you push it what its
inertia is that's why people stopped
talking about the mass of moving
particles which mass and stop talking
about that and defined Mass to be the
energy a thing at
rest but yes um it is correct that the
more energetic an object is the harder
it is to
defle how do you know if an electron at
rest is Left-Handed or right
handed well in a certain sense it's not
left-handed or
right-handed um an electron at rest the
handedness is the relationship between
the momentum and it's particularly well
defined for high momentum for high
momentum the definition of a
right-handed particle is one whose spin
is along its momentum and the
left-handed particle is one whose spin
is opposite so the answer is that there
is no definition of right-handed and
left-handed for a particle at
rest it's mostly useful for high energy
particles the notion of
handedness so if an electron is at rest
and not interact have a weak interaction
okay this this now you've really pushed
me to the edge of uh okay
so uh all
right there's a subtlety which I haven't
told you about and it's the difference
between what is called chirality and
helicity and I I promise to tell you
about it I I've I've uh been a little
bit loose in what I mean by handedness
so let's back
door the idea of handedness as I've
defined it is especially useful for high
energy particles particles whose
momentum is very large when the particle
is has a very small momentum the
handedness of
it uh is a oh God it's it's I'm I'm
losing my um my it's getting too late
for this we'll come back to it yeah I
will I will explain
that be
in no f is of order 250
gev the higs particle as there's good
evidence that it's a good deal lighter
than
that oh
um High Precision um uh experimental and
theoretical comparison
between the properties the masses of the
Z and W
bosons uh they would have a little they
would respond to changes in the mass of
the higs boson in a certain way and from
experimental knowledge of the masses of
the z& W
boson ER I would say the bound on the
higs Mass is probably that it's less
than 160
gev so that's Les than this 250 g but
not by an order of
magnitude so I want to follow up on a
question I asked earlier about the
possibility of multiple
Minima and it occurs to me that if you
had particles which you didn't see in
Generations then that would that would
get in the way of having multiple Minima
in that potential function that so you
have multiple F values from one
potential function yeah so if you had a
particle that didn't exhibit Generations
then it wouldn't wouldn't make sense
let's let's let's come back to it we
will talk maybe next quarter a great
deal about multiple Minima and what kind
of different physics can take place in
different Minima
um
but simply
stated you can have anything happen
almost anything happen in another
minimum of the potential so I I didn't
want get into that tonight I'm getting
tired as you can see so ask me some more
questions if if the if the energy level
that's required to answer them is low I
will do it but what but uh how about are
we're going to have a class next week
what's next week next Monday I mean are
we at the end of this course or we going
to have another class next week what's
the
date uh this is the ninth lecture nth
lecture well then I suppose we have
another class I know I have to be away
at some point but I don't think that's
till the
18th
um oh
yeah yeah yeah well we don't have to
have two classes and we won't have two
classes because I'll be away for the uh
for the 11th week um but for the 10th
week where which yeah let's meet why
not
sure
okay yeah if I if I recover from
tonight yeah yeah yeah um there are
various uh scenarios for the value of
the higs bosan mass and in some of them
the range of energies is quite is easy
it's the rate and the and the things
that things Decay into sometimes they
Decay into just invisible things so
um uh
the higs boson will not be the first
thing discovered at uh at LHC of course
it may be the first thing to discover if
nothing else is discovered but there's a
lot of room for Discovery before the
higs BOS
on particularly if super
Sy the the phon and the gluon don't seem
to have anti particles is that because
they have zero M no no it has it does
not have to do with their Mass it has to
do with their absence of having any kind
of
charge to distinguish the particle from
the
antiparticle so the photon is uncharged
with respect to any kind of charge that
we know about it doesn't participate in
Weak
interactions uh it's not electrically
charged neutrons neutros have no
charge neutros have no charge they have
an particles they must have weak charge
anti
nutral yeah they also don't have any
conser charges but there are anti nutrin
there are anti oh oh oh that's well are
there anti
neutrinos um
well no some people would say there's
only one kind of nutrino and it's both
left-handed and
right-handed other people would say
there are neutrinos and anti- neutrinos
the point is the neutrinos can mix
together with the anti neutrinos and
form a massive myana particle which is
its own
antiparticle why because it's a
superposition of a particle and an
antiparticle so it's there's some subtle
quantum mechanics
there does the standard model try to
explain why charge font no well yeah
yeah yeah we can talk about that too it
does uh but only yeah it does um
remember neutrinos have weak
charges they interact under the weak
interactions and
so uh the the weak interactions provide
this collection of charges that uh that
we've been discussing and the neutrino
is not uncharged with respect to the
weak interaction uh with respect to the
Z and the W
boson in particular
the neutrino and the anti- neutrino
interact differently with with the
zebon so you might say that with respect
to a zosan the neutrino and anti-
nutrino have opposite
charge uh
and they also have lepton number which
is another conserved
quantity you can production of electron
and nutrino and they have to have the
same
conserve unless the lepton number is not
conserved
any OPP okay all right I I'm nodding my
head yes but I know deep in my heart
that the answer is no and the reason is
that lepton number is not really thought
to be
conserved right and it's connected with
this mayorana story and the mass of
neutrinos uh nutrino oscillations can
mix nutrino with anti- nutrino and
things like that you
know for more please visit us at
stanford.edu